Finding Aid for Ira W. Butterfield (1915-1995) Papers 1875-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Ira W. Butterfield (1915-1995) papers
1875-1990
1944-1990
Butterfield, Ira William, 1915-
Records relating to the First Congregational Church of Bay City, Michigan, collected by Ira Butterfield and his father George Butterfield; include correspondence written to wife during World War II while on duty in the Philippines with the Judge Advocate's office; other series concern his activities with the Bay County Council on Juvenile Delinquency, his various campaigns for public office, and his interest in Michigan archaeology; and photographs to be used in political advertisements probably from his campaign for Bay County District Judge in 1974; also photographs taken 1945-1946 while serving in the military with the Judge Advocate's office in the Philippines
90202 AA/2
Sponsor: This finding aid is a product of a project supported by a grant awarded to the Bentley Historical Library and University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology in 2002 by the Division of Preservation and Access of the National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal agency.
10 linear feet in 11 boxes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (donor no. 5169 ) was donated by Ira Butterfield; it came to the library in several accessions, 1990-1995. A small amount of material was transferred by the University of Michigan Museum of Anthropology (donor no. 9273) in 2003.
The collection is open for research.
Ira W. Butterfield was born in Bay City, Michigan on January 30, 1915, the son of George E. Butterfield, a Bay City educator, and Esther Butterfield. He was the valedictorian of Bay City High School's graduating class of 1933. After attending Bay City Junior College, he transferred over to the University of Michigan in 1935. Working on a combined course program in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts and the Law School, Butterfield received his B.A. in 1937 and his law degree in 1940.
Returning to Bay City after his graduation, he served as an assistant to the City Attorney and then in 1942 left to serve as a Law Clerk to the Michigan Supreme Court. In 1944 he was inducted into the infantry and commissioned in 1945. On July 5, 1945 he married the former Eleanor Meyers, and they eventually had two children, Miriam and Robert. He continued his career in the Army by serving in the Judge Advocate General's Department in 1946 while stationed in the Philippines. After the war he returned once again to Bay City and entered private practice.
Ira Butterfield was very active in politics. In 1956 he was elected County Prosecuting Attorney for Bay County, a position which he held for two years, from 1957 to 1958. After an unsuccessful bid for reelection he once again returned to private practice. In 1968 Butterfield was elected to the newly created position of District Judge in the 74th District Court. He served from January 1, 1969 until 1978 when he resigned to accept Governor Milliken's appointment as circuit court judge for the 18th Judicial Circuit. He served here until his term expired January 1, 1981.
Throughout his career Butterfield was active in a variety of professional organizations, including the following: Bay County Bar Association (Treasurer 1943, Vice President 1953, President 1954), and as a member of the State Bar of Michigan, the American Judicature Society, and the American Bar Association. Ira Butterfield also served his community in a variety of volunteer organizational activities, including: the Bay County Council on Juvenile Delinquency (President 1947-49); Bay County Historical Society (President and Treasurer); Michigan Archaeological Society (State President 1956-57); and Gubernatorial Recount Board, Bay County (1950 and 1952).
Ira Butterfield was very interested in the First Congregational Church of Bay City. Along with his father, George Butterfield, Ira Butterfield served the church in various capacities, as moderator, clerk, Sunday school superintendent, chairman of the trustees, and chairman of the deacons.
Of considerable interest to Butterfield while he was associated with the church was the rift that developed in the 1950s between the minister and members of the congregation. The Reverend Thomas Vernon became minister of the church in 1947, and by the early 1950s disagreement had developed between him and one section of the congregation (which included the Butterfield family) over his theology. This group felt that the minister was forcing out longtime members who disagreed with his views, and "packing" the membership with his own supporters. The minister, in return, charged that the dissenters were traditionalists who were intolerant of any beliefs other than their own.
The controversy escalated throughout the 1950s. The dissenting group accused the minister and his supporters of altering records and manipulating the church constitution, church membership, and church organizations in order to move the church away from congregationalism. The minister charged that the dissenting group represented a minority which would use any means to get rid of him because of his liberal views, and insisted that his actions were true to the spirit of congregationalism. The move on the national level during the late 1950s to merge the Congregational and Evangelical and Reformed denominations into the United Church of Christ added further complexity to the situation, with the minister siding with those who wanted to remain more strictly congregational.
Despite the protests, in 1957 the congregation voted to retain Rev. Vernon as minister. Eventually, the dissenting group ceased to participate in church activities, organized itself into the Christian Congregational Association, hired a lawyer, and moved to call an Ecclesiastical Council of the Central Association of Congregational Christian Churches of Michigan. They petitioned to have the church declared extinct as a congregational church, and if successful, their goal was to proceed to civil courts to have the corporation dissolved and to regain control of the church property.
The Ecclesiastical Council was held on November 13, 1957, and in December it denied the petition to declare the church extinct. The report of the Ecclesiastical Council concluded that each side had some basis for its charges, and sharply criticized the behavior of both parties. The Council recommended that Rev. Vernon resign within one year, and in 1959, Rev. Vernon and some former members of the First Congregational Church founded the First Unitarian Church of Bay City.
After the controversy, the Butterfield family again became active in church affairs, attempting to reverse a steady decline in membership. By 1985 the First Congregational Church was sharing a minister with the First United Church of Christ of Bay City and consideration was being given to a merger of the two churches. The First Congregational Church decided against this option, however, and continued to operate separately.
Ira Butterfield died in 1995.
The bulk of the collection consists of records pertaining to the First Congregational Church of Bay City, Michigan collected by Ira Butterfield and his father, George Butterfield, over a period of more than 80 years. The rest of the collection consists of the personal papers of Ira Butterfield. These papers relate to his experiences in World War II, his legal career, charitable and personal interests. The majority of these personal papers relate to his various campaigns for public office. The collection is divided into six series: First Congregational Church, Bay City, MI; Military Service; Bay County Council on Delinquency; Campaigns; Archaeology and Photographs. Although the collection contains some records dating from before 1944, the majority date from 1944 to 1990. Some earlier materials may be found in the First Congregational Church of Bay City collection, also held by the Bentley Library.
Subjects:
Archaeology.; Church buildings--Michigan--Bay City.; Bay County Council on Juvenile Delinquency (Mich.); Butterfield, Ira William, 1915-; Congregational churches--Michigan--Bay City.; First Congregational Church (Bay City, Mich.); Juvenile delinquency--Michigan--Bay County.; Petroglyphs--Michigan--Sanilac County.; World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.
Subjects - Visual Material:
World War, 1939-1945--Philippines.; Philippines--History--1898-1946.
Contributors:
Butterfield, George Ernest, 1883-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- First Congregational Church, Bay City, MI
  The First Congregational Church, Bay City, MI series consists of six subseries; Administrative Files, Church Organizations and Committees, Controversy, 1950-1958, National and Regional Materials, George Butterfield Files and Bound Volumes-Church History. The series includes information on the administration and organization of the church as well as church history.
  - Administrative Files, 1875-1990
    The Administrative Files subseries consists of official records, including two bound volumes of clerk's records, minutes of various types of meetings, church newsletters, and church bulletins. Most of these materials continue chronological sequences which begin in the First Congregational Church collection mentioned above. For example, the bound clerk's records from 1875 to 1952 are found in the First Congregational Church collection, while those covering 1952-1984 are found in this collection. Also included are miscellaneous files maintained by Ira Butterfield, containing information about membership, attendance and finances.
    - Records of First Congregational Church of Bay City (Clerk's Record), 1952-1990
      - 1952-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970-1984 (Box 1)
    - Church annual reports
      - 1975-1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980-1985, 1990 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Board of Trustees
      - 1918-1950 (Box 1)
      - 1951-1956 (Box 1)
      - 1962-1964 (Box 1)
      - 1965-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1972-1988 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Board of Deacons
      - 1968-1980 (Box 1)
      - 1981 (Box 1)
      - 1982 (Box 1)
      - 1983 (Box 1)
      - 1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985 (Box 1)
      - 1986-1988 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of General Board Meetings, 1949-1957 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Coordinating Committee meeting, June 1978 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Joint Meetings of Deacons and Trustees, 1982-1987 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Council Meetings, 1987 (Box 1)
    - Minutes of Congregational Meetings, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
    - Church newsletters
      - 1976 (Box 1)
      - 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978-1987, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Church bulletins
      - 1914-1975, 1 folders (Box 2)
      - 1976-1989, 14 folders (Box 2)
    - Church officers and list of ministers, 1948-1988 (Box 3)
    - Church constitutions (Box 3)
    - Constitutions, other congregational churches (likely 1950s), undated (Box 3)
    - Church procedures handbook
      - 1959-1989 (Box 3)
      - 1966-1967, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Church property (Box 3)
    - Membership data
      - 1910-1950 (Box 3)
      - 1950-1980 (Box 3)
      - 1980-1990 (Box 3)
      - Membership lists, 1981-1988 (Box 3)
    - Attendance data, 1981-1986 (Box 3)
    - Financial data
      - 1919-1949 (Box 3)
      - 1950-1955 (Box 3)
      - 1956-1969 (Box 3)
      - 1970-1979 (Box 3)
      - 1980-1987 (Box 3)
    - Statistics
      - General, 1875-1984 (Box 3)
      - Membership, 1952-1985 (Box 3)
      - Attendance, 1920-1989 (Box 3)
      - Financial, 1922-1984 (Box 3)
    - Church miscellaneous
      - 1958 (Box 3)
      - 1959 (Box 3)
      - 1960-1985, 26 folders (Box 4)
      - 1986-1989, 1 folders (Box 4)
  - Church Organizations and Committees, 1901-1989
    The Church Organizations and Committees subseries contains files documenting Ira Butterfield's involvement in various church activities, largely from the 1960s through the 1980s. Of interest are various church self-study reports, reports of pastoral search committees, documentation of the proposed merger with First United Church of Christ in 1985, and materials documenting the Scrooby Club from 1910 to the 1950s.
    - Boy Scouts, 1901-1932 (Box 4)
    - Central Association of Michigan Conference, miscellaneous, 1962-1979 (Box 4)
    - Church Growth Steering Committee, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Church self-study committees
      - 1969, 2 folders (Box 4)
      - 1982 (Box 4)
      - Haller-Stutsman Report, 1984 (Box 4)
    - Consultation on Church Union, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Memorial Committee, 1978-1984 (Box 4)
    - Pastoral Search Committee
      - 1969 (Box 4)
      - 1970 (Box 4)
      - 1977 (Box 4)
      - 1985
        - Church profile (Box 4)
        - Materials studied (Box 4)
        - Help from state and national organizations (Box 4)
        - Committee minutes (Box 4)
        - Merger Study Committee, 1985-1986; 2 folders (Box 4)
        - Consolidation Committee, 1985-1986
          - 1985-1986, 1 folders (Box 4)
          - 1985-1986, 1 folders (Box 5)
        - Consolidation Transcript, 1986 (Box 5)
        - Consolidation, legal questions, 1986 (Box 5)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - Pastoral Relations Committee, 1978-1985 (Box 5)
    - Pilgrim Fellowship
      - 1948-1970, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Achievement awards, 1963-1971 (Box 5)
    - Pulpit Supply, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Religious Education Committee, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Scrooby Club
      - Scrapbook, 1907-1953 (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5)
      - Mary Hartley, 1944-1956 (Box 5)
      - Banquet programs and announcements, 1910-1952 (Box 5)
      - Correspondence
        - 1939-1944 (Box 5)
        - 1945 (Box 5)
        - 1946-1948 (Box 5)
        - 1949 (Box 5)
        - 1950 (Box 5)
        - 1951 (Box 5)
        - 1952-1958 (Box 5)
    - Young People's Society of Christian Endeavor, 1908-1930 (Box 5)
    - Christian Endeavor World, 1923 (Box 5)
  - Ministerial Controversy, 1950-1958
    Two linear feet of materials collected by Ira Butterfield during the rift in the church make up the Ministerial Controversy, 1950-1958 subseries. The materials include background materials collected in the process of deciding on a course of action and materials collected specifically in preparation for the Ecclesiastical Council. The materials have been retained in their original order. A narrative of the controversy written by Ira Butterfield may be found at the beginning of the subseries, the petition to the Ecclesiastical Council is located near the end, and the Council's report is located in the folder entitled "Correspondence and notes, 1958."
    - Narrative of controversy by Ira Butterfield, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Background materials
      - Manipulation of membership rolls (Box 6)
      - Annual and semi-annual meetings, minutes and notes, 1950-1958 (Box 6)
      - Board meeting minutes, 1950-1958 (Box 6)
      - Investigations (Box 6)
      - Documents (Box 6)
      - Sermons, 1952-1958 (Box 6)
      - Program material (Box 6)
      - Men's Service Club (Box 6)
      - Plymouth Club (Box 6)
      - Jubilee Booklet (Box 6)
      - Building Committee (Box 6)
      - Council of Churches fight (Box 6)
      - Notes, summaries and statements (Box 6)
      - Politics and social action (Box 6)
      - Church constitution revision (Box 6)
      - Christian Congregational Association (Box 6)
      - Legal action preparation, 1957 (Box 6)
      - Vernon campaign, 1957 (Box 6)
      - Merger of Congregational and Evangelical Reformed to form United Church of Christ, 1957-1961; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - National Association of Congregational Christian Churches, 1958-1960 (Box 6)
    - Ecclesiastical Council, 1957-1958
      - Brief on law, 1957 (Box 6)
      - Charge 1, congregation denied right to vote on reception of new members (Box 6)
      - Charge 2, congregation denied right to vote on admission/dismissal of members (Box 6)
      - Charge 3, illegal committees (Box 6)
      - Charges 4 and 5, arbitrary admission/dismissal of members (Box 6)
      - Charge 6, members told to join other churches (Box 6)
      - Charge 7, purge and replacement of leaders (Box 6)
      - Charge 8, misuse of funds (Box 6)
      - Charge 9, manipulation of organizations (Box 6)
      - Charge 10, manipulation of Pilgrim Fellowship (Box 6)
      - Charge 11, church records altered (Box 6)
      - Charge 12, church not functioning as congregational (Box 6)
      - Trial brief for proceedings of Ecclesiastical Council, November 1957; 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Possible exhibits (Box 7)
      - Rebuttal (Box 7)
      - Correspondence and notes
        - 1957 (Box 7)
        - 1958 (Box 7)
        - Notes, undated (Box 7)
        - Notes, unsorted, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
      - Christian Congregational Association
        - Items needing research, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
        - Mailing list, 1957 (Box 7)
      - Rev. Vernon's unitarian activities (Box 7)
      - Financial investigation (Box 7)
      - Newsletters, 1956 (Box 7)
      - Social Action Committee, 1957-1958 (Box 7)
      - Preparation for Ecclesiastical Council, 1957; 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Petition to Central Association of Congregational Christian Churches and Ministers of Michigan, 1957 (Box 7)
      - Post-controversy, 1959-1961 (Box 7)
  - Congregational and United Church of Christ National and Regional Materials, 1941-1989
    The National and Regional Materials subseries consists largely of newsletters and miscellaneous publications of the Michigan Conference of the United Church of Christ, dating from the 1960s to the 1980s. The George Butterfield Files contain materials relating to the First Congregational Church collected by George Butterfield, including church correspondence dated 1910-1911, various Sunday School materials, and materials on the 1950s controversy. The Bentley Library also holds a separate collection of George Butterfield's personal papers.
    - National and regional materials, 1941-1969 (Box 7)
    - National materials, 1980-1989; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - United Church News, 1985-1987 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Conference
      - Covenant Association, 1983-1987 (Box 7)
      - General, 1983-1985 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Conference News
      - 1969-1970 (Box 7)
      - 1971-1972 (Box 8)
      - 1973-1974 (Box 8)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 8)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 8)
      - 1979-1980 (Box 8)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 8)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 8)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 8)
  - George Butterfield Files
    The subseries Bound Volumes-Church History (titled by Butterfield "Ephemeral Bits and Pieces") consists of two bound volumes of collected materials. The volumes contain a wide variety of information on church history, from 1893-1990, including newspaper clippings, photographs, Sunday school materials, correspondence, and radio announcements. A name and subject index is located at the back of each volume.
    - Church correspondence, 1910-1911
      - A-B (Box 8)
      - C-D (Box 8)
      - E-H (Box 8)
      - I-N (Box 8)
      - O-S (Box 8)
      - T-Z (Box 8)
    - Church correspondence, 1917-1959 (Box 8)
    - Weekly notes, Sunday school, 1929-1933 (Box 8)
    - Sunday school, 1924-1935 (Box 8)
    - Prudential Committee, 1923-1944 (Box 8)
    - Rev. Vernon, 1953-1958 (Box 8)
    - Controversy, 1950-1958; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Christian Congregational Association, 1956-1958 (Box 8)
    - Congregational denomination materials, 1905-1982 (Box 8)
  - Church History (titled "Ephemeral Bits and Pieces") (Bound Volumes)
    - 1893-1957 (Box 9)
    - 1958-1990 (Box 9)
- Military Service
  The Military Service series documents Ira Butterfield's experiences serving in the United States army. The series is composed of correspondence with his wife, his father, and others, as well as correspondence authored by his brother, George W. Butterfield. The series also contains numerous black and white photographs taken whilst Butterfield was stationed in the Philippines, an army scrapbook and servicemen oriented printed materials.
  - General, 1944-1946 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence
    - Family to Ira Butterfield, 1934; 1945-1946 (Box 9)
    - Friends to Ira Butterfield, 1945-1946 (Box 9)
    - George W. Butterfield to family, 1944-1945 (Box 9)
    - Ira Butterfield to Eleanor Butterfield
      - Undated, August-December, 1944 (Box 9)
      - January-March, 1945 (Box 9)
      - April-August, 1945 (Box 9)
      - September-October, 1945 (Box 9)
      - November-December, 1945 (Box 9)
      - January 1946 (Box 9)
      - February-March, 1946 (Box 9)
      - April-September, 1946 (Box 9)
    - Ira Butterfield to family, 1944-1946; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Ira Butterfield to friends, 1946 (Box 9)
    - Ira Butterfield to and from Albert W. Black, 1944-1946 (Box 9)
    - Raymond Schneider to family, 1942-1944 (Box 9)
  - Infantry School Notebooks, 1945; 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Naval Reserve, 1941-1944 (Box 10)
  - Officer's Candidate School Class Picture, 1945 (Folder UA1)
  - Photographs, 1941-1946 (Box 10)
  - Post discharge communications, 1946-1947 (Box 10)
  - Pre-military employment, 1933-1944 (Box 10)
  - Printed Materials
    - Daily Pacifican, Army Newspaper in the Western Pacific, 1946; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946 (Box 10)
    - Sentimental Journey, 1946 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook, 1945-46 (Box 11)
- Bay County Council on Juvenile Delinquency
  The Bay County Council on Juvenile Delinquency series consists of materials collected by Ira Butterfield during his tenure as the council's president, 1947-1949. The materials are mostly of an administrative nature, and include correspondence, minutes, reports, and notes. Ira Butterfield had arranged these papers according to document type (facts, committees, general, minutes, Youth Council, etc.); this order has been maintained.
  - 1935-1948, 2 folders (Box 10)
- Campaigns
  The Campaigns series best documents Ira Butterfield's quest for political office from 1954 to 1974. These materials, divided chronologically by election year, consist of a sampling of promotional literature, correspondence, advertising, and official documents pertaining either to the campaign or to his election to office. These materials are also an excellent source of biographical information.
  - 1954 (Box 10)
    (Prosecuting Attorney, Bay County)
  - 1956 (Box 10)
  - 1958 (Box 10)
  - 1960 (Box 10)
    (Judge of Probate, Bay County)
  - 1968
    (District Judge, Bay County)
    - Affidavits, certificates, election legals (Box 10)
    - Campaign Letters and ephemeral (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Newspaper advertising (Box 10)
  - 1974
    - Affidavits, certificates, election legals (Box 10)
    - Campaign letters and ephemera (Box 10)
    - Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Newspaper advertising (Box 10)
    - Press, radio, and television releases (Box 10)
    - Telephone survey (Box 10)
- Archaeology
  Ira Butterfield's continuing personal interest in Michigan archaeology is best reflected in the Archaeology series. This series is divided into two subseries: Correspondence, 1955-1993 and Sanilac Petroglyphs.
  The Correspondence, 1955-1993 subseries consists primarily of letters to and from amateur and professional Michigan archaeologists. A variety of sites and finds are discussed along with issues such as the placement of historical markers.
  The Sanilac Petroglyphs subseries consists of correspondence, photographs and maps detailing the Sanilac County, Michigan petroglyphs site and the steps undertaken to create a state park to protect it. The Petroglyphs site consists of rock carvings created by Native Americans.
  - Correspondence (Box 10)
    - Cleland, Charles, 1971-1973 (Box 10)
    - Dustin, Fred, 1984 (Box 10)
    - Evans, Oren F., 1958 (Box 10)
    - Fitting, James E., 1963-1973 (Box 10)
    - Hays, Donald R., 1971-1990 (Box 10)
    - "Integrating Archaeology into a Cooperative Venture,", 1974 (Box 10)